Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, חודש טוב, Chodesh tov, not חודש טוב,
Chodesh tov, גוט מועד. Gut moed. Today is the fifth day of
the עומר. Omer. We start with the משנה Mishna on the bottom
of כב עמוד ב. Chaf beis amud bais. I should start before
we get to the משנה Mishna to just quickly review some key
points from the גמרא Gemara you did on שבת Shabbos because it's
very central for הלכה למעשה. Halacha l'maaseh. You saw the position of
רב יהודה Reb Yehuda that said אתי רבים ומבטלי מחיצה, Asi rabbim
u-mivattli mechitza, that the רבים rabbim going through a מחיצה mechitza negate
it. And that's obviously critical because it leads to the position that
you cannot have an עירוב eruv around a street that is a
real רשות הרבים reshus harabbim because then the רבים rabbim will go
through the עירוב eruv and they will consider it, they'll go through
the fictional wall of the צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach and it will
no longer be considered a מחיצה. mechitza. Now for רב יהודה Reb
Yehuda itself it wasn't a problem because he held two מחיצות mechitzos
were enough. But if you combine רב יהודה Reb Yehuda with the
position of the חכמים chachamim that you need three מחיצות, mechitzos, that's
why practically you cannot have an עירוב eruv around something that is
designated as a true רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Now the other critical
issue that did come up in the גמרא Gemara was the question
of that why isn't an island a רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid? Why
don't you just use sort of like the drop of the sea
wall to count as a רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid?
And the question at the end of the גמרא Gemara which גמרא
Gemara never answers is, well, yeah, like why not?
So that never gets fully answered by the גמרא. Gemara.
And especially now if you say אתי רבים ומבטלי מחיצה Asi rabbim
u-mivattli mechitza you could say, well, if there's travel over the edges
of the island then that negates the wall. But אתי רבים ומבטלי
מחיצה Asi rabbim u-mivattli mechitza really only negates the wall where there's
a crossover. So if you imagine, let's say Manhattan, so fine, where
there's the G.W. Bridge that will not be considered surrounded by walls
because that's breaking through the מחיצה mechitza of Manhattan island. But everywhere
else why not just use, assuming again you have enough of a
drop by the sea wall or by the river wall or whatever,
why not just say that it's מחיצות mechitzos because of the river
wall? And that's never really fully answered in the גמרא. Gemara. And
it seems that there are two answers here. One is that תוספות
Tosafos says when they're just natural walls and not manmade everybody would
agree אתי רבים ומבטלי מחיצה. Asi rabbim u-mivattli mechitza. Again it doesn't
really answer the point because, but it seems like תוספות Tosafos would
say further that in that case when they're just natural made the
presence of the רבים rabbim inside the מחיצות, mechitzos, not just the
point that they cross through, but their presence inside negates the entire
wall altogether. Not exactly clear what that answer is. The רמבן Ramban
says an idea that's more quoted in the פוסקים, poskim, which is
that you have to be able to see yourself contained within the
מחיצות. mechitzos. And when they're natural like this and so far apart,
well he doesn't emphasize natural, you don't see yourself contained within the
מחיצות. mechitzos. The question is what's like the limit of that? Because
some פוסקים poskim say that well that would mean let's say if
they're ten miles apart. Well, so not all islands are ten miles
by ten miles and maybe it should work. So that's another very
important issue which is why do you not, can't you at the
end of the day use the walls of an island, especially if
you don't hold of ומבטלי מחיצה, u-mivattli mechitza, but even if you
do, at places where they're not crossing through the walls. The third
important issue from yesterday's דף daf was the issue about יהושע Yehoshua
gave over these roads to the רבים, rabbim, but if they're hard
to traverse they remained own private. How does ownership affect the definition
of a רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim? So תוספות Tosafos right there said
it was just combined with the idea that these roads are very
impassable. So if you combined it with a hard-to-pass road plus that
it's privately owned so in no way could it be envisioned as
a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, then we would say, we would not
say אתי רבים ומבטלי מחיצה Asi rabbim u-mivattli mechitza
and therefore that would limit our ability to say the רבים rabbim
negates the מחיצה. mechitza. That's תוספות's Tosafos position, it combines the idea
of private ownership with the problem about being מבטלי mivattli the מחיצה.
mechitza. רמבן Ramban though in a later דף, daf, although it seems
to go against the גמרא, Gemara, says that something is not a
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim unless it literally is owned by the public
regardless of the presence or absence of מחיצות. mechitzos. So according to
the רמבן Ramban a privately owned street would be exempt from being
a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So anyway those are critical issues that
came up on yesterday's דף: daf: A, in reverse order, the issue
of ownership; B, the question of island walls making a רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid even in a very large space; and C, the principle
of אתי רבים ומבטלי מחיצה. Asi rabbim u-mivattli mechitza. Okay so we
now resume and look at the משנה mishna on the bottom of
כב עמוד ב. Chaf beis amud bais. אחד בור הרבים ובאר הרבים
ובאר היחיד עושים לה פסים. Echad bor harabbim u-ve'er harabbim u-ve'er hayachid
osim lo pasim.
So this is again the special leniency of פסי ביראות posi biraos
and whether it is a communal well or a communal, like
a בור bor is of collected water. or a live well, a
well of underground spring, ובאר יחיד uveer yachid or a private live
well, עושים לו פסים, osim lo pasim, you can do this פסים,
pasim, again the פסים pasim is a leniency because it's not fully
surrounded by walls, but that would be okay if it is a
regardless of what the configuration or what type of well it is,
with the one exception of a לבור יחיד labor yachid עושים לו
מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים osim lo mechitza gevoha asara tefachim דברי רבי
עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. If it is privately owned and it is
a well of collected water, then that would have to be a
real מחיצה mechitza all the way around because as we've seen before,
the fact that it's collected water means it could dry up and
the fact that it's owned by a private person means that nobody
will be around to remind you, and we're afraid you'll come to
use this not 100% wall when there's no longer the justification. The
other issue the גמרא Gemara also did throw in about the באר
בור be'er bor issue was whether it was fit for human consumption,
although here that does not seem to be what dictates because then
you would never allow the case of the בור, bor, even if
it was owned by the רבים. rabim. So that's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. רבי יהודה בן בבא אומר Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava omer אין
עושים פסים אלא לבאר רבים בלבד. ein osim pasim ela lebeer rabim
bilvad. Very restrictive, it has to be A communal and B it
has to be a באר be'er live water. So that's why it
might be if it's communal you might already be addressing the concern
and that it would people will forget so the there the additional
combination of live water might have to be that it's fit for
human consumption as well. Anyway, these are very this this very restrictive
position. ולשאר uleshaar and all other things עושים חגורה osim chagora you
make a belt literally a real wall גבוה עשרה טפחים gevoha asara
tefachim ten טפחים tefachim high. Okay,
so now we've seen a lot of limitations of when we allow
the פסי ביראות. pashei biraos. Maybe only for the עולי רגלים olei
regalim or for and only when it's needed for their animals, if
you made it for their animals maybe it would be allowed for
others. And now according to רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben
Bava only if it was for a באר be'er and owned by
the רבים. rabim. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara top
of כ"ג עמוד א'. chaf gimel amud alef. אמר רב יוסף אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יהודה בן בבא. Amar Rav Yosef
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha keRabbi Yehuda ben Bava. We rule
like רבי יהודה בן בבא. Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava. ואמר רב יוסף
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל לא הותרו פסי ביראות אלא בבאר מים
חיים בלבד. Ve'amar Rav Yosef amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel lo hutru
pashei biraos ela beveer mayim chayim bilvad. They only allowed it for
a live well of water water meaning not collected water but coming
from an underground spring. וצריכא Utzricha he has to tell both because
aren't they isn't that what רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben
Bava said? אי אשמעינן הלכה כרבי יהודה בן בבא Ei ashmeinan halacha
keRabbi Yehuda ben Bava had you just said we rule like him,
הוה אמינא דרבים ואפילו מכונסים. hava amina derabim ve'afilu mechunasim. Well what
we're underscoring about רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava is
his position of רבים. rabim. Maybe we would have thought that the
emphasis would not have been on his position of באר be'er but
on רבים. rabim. And therefore if it's owned by the public even
if it is gathered rainwater because the issue is again concern that
will dry up so as long as it's owned by public no
concern.
ואפילו מכונסים. Ve'afilu mechunasim. והאי דקתני באר הרבים Vehai deka tani beer
harabim so why does he say באר? be'er? לאפוקי מדרבי עקיבא Le'apukei
midRabbi Akiva because because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said by a באר
be'er you don't need רבים. rabim. He's saying by a באר be'er
even by a באר be'er you need רבים. rabim. קמשמע לן Kamashma
lan that it's not just the רבים rabim that he's that he's
demanding but what we're emphasizing we פסקן pasken but even the fact
that it is a באר. be'er. דלא הותרו פסי ביראות אלא בבאר
מים חיים. Delo hutru pashei biraos ela beveer mayim chayim.
So he has to emphasize I'm not only פסקן pasken by him
by רבים rabim but also that it has to be a באר.
be'er. ואי אשמעינן באר מים חיים Ve'ei ashmeinan beer mayim chayim had
you just said that line הוה אמינא לא שנא דרבים ולא שנא
דיחיד hava amina lo shana derabim velo shana deyachid that it wouldn't
matter whether it was public or private as long as it's live
water. Again maybe because of the human consumption or because live water
won't dry up. קמשמע לן הלכה כרבי יהודה בן בבא Kamashma lan
halacha keRabbi Yehuda ben Bava
that we rule like him that we require both criteria. Now I
mean you could imagine he could have said לבאר מים חיים ושל
רבים בלבד. leveer mayim chayim veshel rabim bilvad. Anyway, but by saying
both he made it very clear that we rule like him. So
now again we have a very serious limit on this case of
פסי ביראות pashei biraos under what circumstances justify its use. Now let's
take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. Now we get onto
another topic which picks up on a theme mentioned in the first
משנה. Mishnah. ועוד אמר רבי יהודה בן בבא, Ve'od amar Rabbi Yehuda
ben Bava, the same way רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben
Bava had a stringency before, he has the following stringency:
הגינה והקרפף שהן שבעים אמה ושיריים על שבעים אמה ושיריים. Hagina vehakarpef
shehen shivim ama veshirayim al shivim ama veshirayim. If you have a
garden or like a type of a you know like just an
open space that is surrounded that is 70 and and change by
70 and change. The change here is what we'll see in the
גמרא Gemara two thirds אמות amos because that's roughly the square root
of 5,000. Again the size that is a is a is בית
סאתים beis sasayim is learned from the משכן. Mishkan. The משכן Mishkan
was 50 אמה ama by 100 which is 5,000 square אמות. amos.
And if you do the square root of 5,000 אמות, amos, you
will get to 70.71.
So 70 and two thirds is 70.66. So it's very close. So
that's how we're describing something that is the size of 5,000 square
אמות. amos. Now we remember in the first משנה, Mishnah, there was
a position that the
that the פסי ביראות pashei biraos could only be a בית סאתים
beis sasayim and no bigger. And then the pushback was and that
was the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And then the response
was "No, no, no, when did they limit it? That was only
for
גינה וקרפף," gina vekarpef, a... You're just there to take care of
your business. So it's a very hard to define exactly the line
between using it for human needs and you know and at what
point does it no longer become considered הוקף לדירה. hukaf l'dira. We'll
see some examples in the גמרא Gemara but it's a very hard
to precisely define that difference. But anyway when it's deemed to be
not הוקף לדירה hukaf l'dira then it's not a full type of
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. People don't really live there. So we
limit it to the size of בית סאתים. beit satayim. So there
was a debate whether you consider the well of פסי ביראות pasi
beiraot to be the same, and the basic חכמים chakhamim of the
first משנה mishna was that is for human use. People go there
and they use the well. Interestingly even though it's primarily for the
animals, but they bring their animals there too. But again whether that
would suffice is unclear. But that's for human use, so that is
that does not have a limit. But if it is לא הוקף
לדירה, lo hukaf l'dira, not really so much for human habitation, then
it's limited to the size of בית סאתים. beit satayim. So let's
take a look now. That is the governing principle or issue of
the משנה. mishna. So ואמר רבי יהודה בן בבא. ve'amar Rabbi Yehuda
ben Bava. רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava also said
another stringency. הגינה והקרפף שהן שבעים אמה ושירים
על שבעים אמה ושירים. hagina vehakarpaf shehen shiv'im ama veshirayim al shiv'im
ama veshirayim. So you have something that's basically a garden, predominantly not
a place of human habitation, that's seventy and change by seventy and
change.
המוקפת גדר גבוה עשרה טפחים. hamukefet geder gavoha asara tefachim. It's got
a wall ten טפחים. tefachim. Again we're no longer talking about a
פסי ביראות. pasi beiraot. It's got a real wall all around it.
You can carry in it. Fine. But then he adds ובלבד שיהא
בה שומירה או בית דירה. uvilvad sheyehei ba shomira o beit dira.
Only if there is a guardhouse or some type of a house
inside of that space. או שתהא סמוכה לעיר. o shetehei smucha la'ir.
Or it's right by the city so it's basically considered to be
something that is regular access by people. So for him even if
it is ראוי לדירה, ra'uy l'dira, הוקף לדירה, hukaf l'dira, it has
this limit. Now of course would that really be all the time?
Meaning like if you really had a courtyard in front of your
house, it couldn't be more than this size?
So תוספות Tosafot says no, you know, this is primarily something that
is לא הוקף לדירה. lo hukaf l'dira. It's really a garden. You
just afterwards maybe like added some type of a thing to make
it a little bit more for habitation. That he says isn't good
enough. Something that really it started with the house and then also
the house came first and then you built some type of a
yard and surrounded it with a wall around it, that would be
a different story. But something that basically is a garden and the
house or whatever was an afterthought, for him that's not enough and
it's still לא הוקף לדירה lo hukaf l'dira and limited to בית
סאתים. beit satayim. That's his position. רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer.
Now רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the סתם רבי יהודה stam Rabbi Yehuda
is not רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava but רבי
יהודה בר אלעאי. Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai. So he says, בר אלעאי
אומר אפילו אין בה אלא בור ושיח ומערה מטלטלין בתוכה. bar Ilai
omer afilu ein ba ela bor vesiach ume'ara metaltelin betocha. You don't
need a full house but you do need something to make it
a little bit more considered to be sort of like, you know,
ראוי לדירה. ra'uy l'dira. You need to or to justify the size
of בית סאתים. beit satayim. You need there to be a well,
like our first משנה, mishna, or some type of an irrigation ditch
and so on. So again according to both of them
following תוספות, Tosafot, if it's a real הוקף לדירה, hukaf l'dira, no
limit. But if it's fundamentally a garden, then even then A, if
it doesn't have anything that makes it fit with דירה, dira, you're
not even allowed בית סאתים. beit satayim. What are you allowed? Maybe
nothing. Maybe if it's not הוקף לדירה hukaf l'dira at all, you
can't carry in it at all. You need some type of a
thing that makes it a little bit more הוקף לדירה. hukaf l'dira.
You need a house or a guardhouse or maybe a well. Okay?
And then you're allowed up to בית סאתים. beit satayim. That's their
position. But without that, not at all. But maybe with a house,
a real house, then maybe you'd be allowed no limit. רבי עקיבא
אומר. Rabbi Akiva omer. Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says and this
is the way we rule, אפילו אין בה אחת מכל אלו מטלטלין
בתוכה. afilu ein ba achat mikol elu metaltelin betocha. Forget those little
things.
You can carry. You're allowed up to בית סאתים beit satayim even
if it's completely לא הוקף לדירה. lo hukaf l'dira. ובלבד שיהא בה
שבעים אמה ושירים על שבעים אמה ושירים uvilvad sheyehei ba shiv'im ama
veshirayim al shiv'im ama veshirayim as long again reiterating what we said
before it doesn't exceed seventy and change by seventy and change. Okay
so again if it is fundamentally הוקף לדירה, hukaf l'dira, I'm following
תוספות Tosafot here, if it's like a house and then you have
a yard that's and then, you know, fundamentally it starts with a
house, everybody would agree no limit. If it's fundamentally לא הוקף לדירה,
lo hukaf l'dira, that's where they debate. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
even that I allow you up to בית סאתים beit satayim and
the other two positions רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava
and the סתם רבי יהודה stam Rabbi Yehuda say no, if it's
fundamentally לא הוקף לדירה lo hukaf l'dira you're not allowed anything until
you have some type of a thing that makes it a little
bit more לדירה. ledira. Once you have that, then we'll give you
up to בית סאתים. beit satayim. We rule like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. Fine. רבי יוסי אומר. Rabbi Yosi omer. Now רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi says אפילו ארכה פי שנים ברחבה מטלטלין בתוכה. afilu orka pi
shenayim berachba metaltelin betocha. It doesn't have to be square. square, it
could even be rectangular even if the length is twice of the
width. Again, it's like the חצר chatzer of the משכן Mishkan which
was exactly that, fifty by a hundred. So he doesn't argue about
the limit of בית סאתיים, beis satayim, but he says it doesn't
have to be square. It sounds like for רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
anything that exceeds a perfect square would not be allowed. And I
have to tell you I don't understand this because okay, but let's
say your yard isn't a perfect square. So בית סאתיים beis satayim
you're not allowed. Are you allowed less than בית סאתיים? beis satayim?
Are you allowed half that size? And it could be rectangular? Does
no matter how small it be it always has to be a
perfect square? Pretty bizarre saying that if it's לא הוקף לדירה lo
hukaf ledira it always has to be a perfect square. But anyway
we will see more of that in the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי אלעאי, Amar Rebbe Ilai,
שמעתי, shamati, I heard, so said רבי אלעאי Rebbe Ilai I heard
מרבי אליעזר meRebbe Eliezer
ואפילו הוא כבית כור vaafilu hu kebeis kor that he says that
there's no limit presumably even if it's לא הוקף לדירה lo hukaf
ledira it could be בית כור beis kor which is much larger
than בית סאתיים. beis satayim. No limit. וכן שמעתי ממנו Vechein shamati
mimenu I heard from him, אנשי חצר ששכח אחד מהן ולא עירב
ביתה, anshei chatzer sheshachach echad mehen velo eirev beita, let's say you
have a חצר chatzer totally unrelated issue, but these are just three
things he heard from רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. If the people of
a courtyard, you know, all got together with an עירוב eiruv but
one guy forgot to join in. So what do you do? So
he basically negates his רשות reshus to them. He sort of like
says I don't hold on to the personal ownership of my רשות,
reshus, you know, for the sake of שבת, Shabbos, which means that
it's not a distinct רשות reshus and therefore everybody is allowed still
allowed to carry. So how does that impact carrying in and out
of his house? So רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer said if he forgot
to do this, אסור להכניס ולהוציא לו אבל להם מותר. asur lehachnis
ulehotzi lo aval lahem mutar.
He can't bring stuff in and out of his house to the
courtyard but they can. So the negating of his רשות reshus actually
not only allows the use of the courtyard but allows the people
of the courtyard to bring into his house. It's just he can't
go from bring from his house into the courtyard. We don't rule
that way. We rule that the courtyard is okay but his house
remains off-limits for everybody. And number three that I heard, וכן שמעתי
ממנו vechein shamati mimenu I also heard מרבי אליעזר meRebbe Eliezer שיוצאין
בארקבלון בפסח. sheyotzin bearkavlin bePesach.
Look at this. So we have another tie-in to פסח Pesach in
addition to עולה לרגל. olei leregel. He says you could use this
type of a vegetable for מרור maror by פסח, Pesach, ארקבלין. arkavlin.
So these are three interesting positions he had, all more lenient than
the standard position out there. וחזרתי על כל תלמידיו, Vechazarti al kol
talmidav, I went over, I looked, you know, I asked all of
his students ובקשתי לי חבר uvikashti li chaveir and I looked for
somebody who would be my colleague who heard the same report from
him and ולא מצאתי velo matzasi and I did not find anybody.
So presumably, you know, maybe I wondered whether he had who knows
what that means. I wondered whether he had retracted it, I wondered
I knew I for sure that he did hold it but I
felt bad that I had nobody else to back me up. Anyway,
interesting little side point about רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer leniency here that
there's no limit of בית סאתיים. beis satayim. Also interesting to note
that רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer is the one who never said anything
he did not hear from his רבותיו rabosav and very much was
about, you know, just passing on traditions. So the idea that he
wanted to reinforce this tradition fits in with a student of רבי
אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
גמרא Gemara first starts with a little sort of literal literary point.
מאי תנא דקתני ועוד? Mai tanna de'katani ve'od?
Why did he say ועוד? ve'od? רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rebbe Yehuda
ben Beseira not only said that, he also said this. What's the
point? אילימא משום דתנא ליה חדא לחומרא וקתני אחריתי משום הכי קתני
ועוד, ilima mishum detana lei chada lechumra ukatani achriti mishum hachi katani
ve'od,
very reasonable. First רבי יהודה בן בבא Rebbe Yehuda ben Bava was
strict in the previous משנה mishnah only a באר be'er of the
רבים rabbim and here he is strict and saying that even if
you have a little house in your that even if you have
a garden that's בית סאתיים, beis satayim, that's not acceptable until you
put a house there. So another חומרא chumra even though conceptually unrelated.
גמרא Gemara says I'll show you that's not the pattern. We can
have two consecutive חומרות chumros of the same תנא tanna and we
won't say
ועוד ve'od if they're unrelated. דאמר רבי יהודה דתנא ליה חדא לחומרא,
De'amar Rebbe Yehuda detana lei chada lechumra, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda now
this is the רבי יהודה ברבי אלעאי Rebbe Yehuda berabi Ilai not
the רבי יהודה בן בבא, Rebbe Yehuda ben Bava, the סתם רבי
יהודה. stam Rebbe Yehuda. So he had one he said one חומרא
chumra וקתני אחריתי vukatni achriti and another חומרא chumra ולא קתני ועוד
velo katani ve'od and it didn't say ועוד. ve'od. Now it doesn't
tell you where, but if you've been paying attention since the beginning
of the פרק perek you know where because at the first beginning
of the פרק perek רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said
that the פסי ביראות pasi biraos also is limited to בית סאתיים.
beis satayim. That was considered to be לא הוקף לדירה, lo hukaf
ledira, not made for habitation and the rabbis argued. And then afterwards
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said that you can't have a פסי ביראות
pasi biraos around a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So he has two
משניות mishnayos juxtaposing both of them חומרות chumros and didn't say ועוד.
ve'od. So why did we say it here and not there?
So גמרא Gemara says no, התם אפסיקוה רבנן הכא לא אפסיקוה רבנן.
hasam afsikua rabbanan hacha lo afsikua rabbanan. You know
there they weren't immediately juxtaposed. If you remember the first משנה mishnah
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said by פסי ביראות pasi biraos it can't
be more than בית סאתיים beis satayim and then the rabbis said
oh no they only... It limited בית סאתים Beis Sasayim to a
גינה gina and a קרפף, karpef, but other things that are made
for habitation like a courtyard and a back alley and da-da-da-da-da, those
things can be as big as you want. And then it said
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about if a רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim goes
through the פסי ביראות. Pasei Bira'os. So you have the whole position
of the חכמים Chachamim intervening, it wasn't immediately juxtaposed. And that's why
we didn't say ועוד. v'od. So the גמרא Gemara says וכל היכא
דאפסיקו רבנן לא תני ועוד? v'chol heicha d'afsiku Rabbanan lo tani v'od?
You mean to tell me anytime that there's a, you know, the
opposite position is stated and so it's not immediately juxtaposed, I mean
it's still two arguments that are juxtaposed, it's just you have the
dissenting voice is stated, you're not going to say ועוד, v'od, even
though they're
juxtaposed? והא רבי אליעזר דסוכה, Veha Rabbi Eliezer deSukkah, so now we're
moving from פסח Pesach to סוכה, Sukkah, there's a position of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by
סוכה Sukkah דאפסיקוה רבנן dafskuh Rabbanan וקא תני ועוד? veka tani v'od?
What's that רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you
have to have 14 meals in a סוכה, Sukkah, two each day,
and the חכמים Chachamim say no, you only have to have the
first night. And then it says ועוד אמר רבי אליעזר, v'od amar
Rabbi Eliezer, if you didn't do the first night you can make
it up on the other nights. So that is two positions intervened
with the רבנן Rabbanan and you have the ועוד. v'od. So here
what's going on? When do you say the ועוד, v'od, when don't
you? And why didn't we say it by רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and we did say it by רבי יהודה בן בבא? Rabbi Yehuda
ben Bava? So the גמרא Gemara says here's the
answer. התם במילתיה הוא דאפסיקוה הכא במילתא אחריתא אפסיקוה. hasam bemilsai hu
de'afsikuh hacha bemilsa achreisa afsikuh. There the Rabbis said back no, you
only have to be in the סוכה Sukkah for the first night.
So that wasn't really a digression. And therefore the next statement of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer which was another חומרא chumra we're going to
say, or not a חומרא, chumra, anyway that actually was more of
a leniency, but anyway you have an immediate next statement of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer we're going to say ועוד v'od because it wasn't
such a digression. But here when רבי, Rabbi, the first משנה, Mishna,
so again we have two cases where it said ועוד. v'od. רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer place by סוכה Sukkah and רבי יהודה בן בבא
Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava here by the פסי ביראות, Pasei Bira'os, by
the well of the רבים, Rabbim, and then the sides of a
garden that was not הוקפה לדירה, hukafla-dira, those places it said ועוד.
v'od. It doesn't say ועוד v'od in our first משנה Mishna of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about the פסי ביראות. Pasei Bira'os. So the
גמרא Gemara says here's the difference. In the two cases it said
ועוד, v'od, either there was no interruption or the interruption was immediately
to the point and on point. In our first משנה Mishna the
interruption was too much of a digression because the חכמים Chachamim didn't
just say back no, a פסי ביראות Pasei Bira'os can be as
big as you want. They went off and they started saying and
the Rabbis only said when did you need something to be the
size of you know, בית סאתים, Beis Sasayim, that was only גינה
gina and קרפף, karpef, but all these other cases you didn't need
it da-da-da-da-da, it was just digressing into other points, it wasn't immediately
on point and therefore it broke it up. Okay so that's the
end of the story. We can say ועוד v'od if you have
two positions that are juxtaposed, maybe they're both חומרות, Chumros, maybe they're
both related, like in one case it was both about the meals
of a סוכה. Sukkah. Where you won't say it is when there
is an intervening position which is not only immediately on point but
also digressing and gets off onto some other point. All right that
was the literary point. Now onto the halachic positions of the משנה.
Mishna. רבי עקיבא אומר אפילו אין בה אחת מכל אלו מטלטלין לתוכה.
Rabbi Akiva omer afilu ein bah achas mikol elu metalmetlin letochah. So
again רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if it is not הוקפה לדירה
hukafla-dira you are still given up to בית סאתים Beis Sasayim and
you don't need something in addition once you have the limit of
בית סאתים. Beis Sasayim. And if it is really הוקפה לדירה hukafla-dira
then there's no limit. The גמרא Gemara says רבי עקיבא היינו תנא
קמא? Rabbi Akiva hainu Tanna Kamma? Isn't רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the
תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? Now which תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? What do
you mean? תנא קמא Tanna Kamma requires that there be a house
or that there be a garden or something. רש"י Rashi says it's
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that we were just referring to at
the very beginning of the פרק perek where there was the position
that פסי ביראות Pasei Bira'os needed to be limited to בית סאתים
Beis Sasayim and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said no, בית סאתים
Beis Sasayim is a גינה gina but anything else no limits and
that basically seemed to indicate that there was no special need by
a garden and you were always given up to בית סאתים. Beis
Sasayim. תוספות Tosafos says it's a more narrow point, not that the
criteria of when you need it is the same. תוספות Tosafos actually
says the question is why did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva repeat 70
and two-thirds? We already said 70 and two-thirds, so what is רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva coming along and saying you don't need a guardhouse
and da-da-da-da-da as long as it's 70 and two-thirds? We just said
that. So the, so either way let's see what the גמרא's Gemara
question is. It sounds like רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva being somewhat redundant,
either the whole position or the emphasis on 70 and two-thirds. So
the גמרא Gemara says איכא בינייהו דבר מועט. ika beineihu davar mu'at.
No the difference is whether it's exactly 70 and two-thirds or 70
and two-thirds plus the change. As I told you 70 and two-thirds
is a little less than the square root of 5,000. So the
גמרא Gemara understands that whether
it goes by בית סאתים, Beis Sasayim, well let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. דתניא, Detanya, רבי יהודה אומר דבר מועט יש
ושבעים אמה ושיריים. Rabbi Yehuda omer davar mu'at yesh v'shivim ama v'shirayim.
There's a little more than 70 and two-thirds that gets you to
the square root of 5,000 ולא נתנו חכמים בו שיעור, v'lo nasnu
Chachamim bo shiur,
and the חכמים Chachamim you know did not give the amount that
is the difference, it's an irrational number anyway. וכמה שיעור סאתים, V'khama
shiur sasayim,
and how much is a סאתים? sasayim? It's a בית סאתיים. beit
satayim. חצר משכן. chatzer mishkan. It's the size of the courtyard of
the משכן, Mishkan, 5,000 square אמות. amot. מנא הני מילי? mena hanei
milei? Where do you get this from? אמר רב יהודה אמר קרא.
amar Rav Yehuda amar kra. The פסוק pasuk says אורך החצר מאה
באמה ורוחב חמישים בחמישים. orech hachatzer meah ba'amah verochav chamishim bachamishim. So
we see it's a 100 by 50, 5,000. But the גמרא Gemara
is not just asking where do you know that it was 5,000,
but where do you know that you use that to limit like
the space of a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid when it's not made
for habitation?
Now, again, this is probably an אסמכתא asmachta because this idea is
really a rabbinic problem that this is a requirement for a רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid. But anyway, where do you see it in the
פסוק? pasuk? So the גמרא Gemara says, why does it say חמישים
בחמישים? chamishim bachamishim?
So אמר תורה—the amar Torah תורה Torah is telling you—טול חמישים וסבב
חמישים. tul chamishim vesovev chamishim. Take the 50 and surround it by
50, which the way רש"י Rashi explains is very creative. If you
want to get the square root of 5,000 but you don't have,
you know, not only do you not
have—you basically don't even have Arabic numerals, which makes it extremely difficult,
right? You don't have digits from zero through nine and 10
and—base 10. It makes it very difficult to do this type of
math. But the way you do it רש"י Rashi says is, you
take the first 50, it's a square 50 by 50. Then you
take the next square 50 by 50 and you start making strips.
So if you imagine you have 50 by 50, you make strips
of 10 by 50 each. So you take those strips and you
take four of them and you put four of those strips on
the four sides of the square. So now you're making a bigger
square. Now it's 70 by 70 because you added 10 on each
side, you know, 10 on the left and the right and 10
on the top and the bottom, 70 by 70. And now you
just have to fill the corners. So you take the little bit
that's left, the strip of 10 by 50, and you, you know,
chop it up and you fill the corners and then you have
a little bit left, so you repeat the process. And that's how
you get to 70 and two-thirds. So that's what we learned by
the fact that it says
חמישים בחמישים—חמישים על חמישים is figure this out, what is the size
of a בית סאתיים beit satayim and the relevance is for the
חצר chatzer of the משכן. Mishkan. And particularly also reinforces רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that speaks about a square. So why did רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva repeat what the תנא קמא Tanna Kama said? To tell
you that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is emphasizing it goes exactly by
70 and two-thirds, whereas the תנא קמא Tanna Kama would allow anything
that was up to—he would also allow it to be bigger, he
would allow the little change up to get to the בית סאתיים.
beit satayim.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
A minute. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues like this: פשטי
דקרא במאי כתיב? pashtei dekra bemai ketiv? So okay, that's all very
nice, but what's the simple sense of the פסוק? pasuk? Why does
it say 50 by 50 if it was 50 by 100? So
אמר אביי: amar Abaye: העמד משכן על שפת חמישים כדי שיהא חמישים
אמה לפניו ועשרים אמה לכל רוח ורוח. ha'ameid Mishkan al sfat chamishim
kedei sheyehei chamishim amah lefanav ve'esrim amah lechol ruach varuach.
To tell you that there really was, although the whole court was
100 by 50, there really was an area of 50 by 50
in front of the משכן. Mishkan. Because you imagine this thing that
was 100 by 50, the משכן Mishkan was 30 by 20—so draw
a line in the middle of the חצר chatzer 50 by 50
and you have two squares of 50 by 50. Put now the
משכן Mishkan behind the line. So if the משכן Mishkan is behind
the line, the open courtyard, you know, before you get to the
משכן Mishkan is 50 by 50. Then you hit the משכן Mishkan
and the משכן, Mishkan, which is 30 by 20, has 10—it has—it
has—excuse me, is 30 by 10, I said that wrong, 30 by
10, has 20 on each side and has 20 behind it, so
also nicely centered. So that's why the 50 by 50, to tell
you that there's a complete open space as it were 50 by
50 before you hit the משכן. Mishkan. Fine, moving on. But that's
the position of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, 70 and two-thirds and exactly
70 and two-thirds even though that's not precisely the square root of
5,000. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר אם הייתה ארכה יתר על רחבה—רבי
אליעזר allows it to be twice the length as the width. So
the גמרא Gemara says: והתניא רבי אליעזר אומר אם הייתה ארכה יתר
על רחבה אפילו אמה אחת אין מטלטלין בתוכה.
vehatanya Rabbi Eliezer omer im hayta orcha yeter al rochba afilu amah
achat ein
metalttelin betocha. Wait a minute, says the גמרא. Gemara. Hold on, did
I skip this line in the משנה? Mishnah? Oh, I—I apologize, I
believe I skipped this line in the משנה. Mishnah. So the משנה
Mishnah has—I'll read the משנה Mishnah again—it says: רבי אליעזר אומר אם
הייתה ארכה יתר על רחבה אפילו אמה אחת אין מטלטלין בתוכה. Rabbi
Eliezer omer im hayta orcha yeter al rochba afilu amah achat ein
metalttelin betocha. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said
it can't even be one אמה amah bigger than a—you know—off of
being
a perfect square. We'll only allow it a perfect square. And then
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says: רבי יוסי אומר אפילו ארכה פי שניים
ברחבה—even Rabbi Yossi omer afilu orcha pi shnayim berochba if it's twice
as long as it is wide. I think I skipped the position
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer when I read the משנה. Mishnah. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it
has to be a perfect square, which also sounded like at least
the way רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was describing it. והתניא רבי אליעזר
אומר אם הייתה ארכה יתר על רחבה פי שניים אפילו אמה אחת
אין מטלטלין בתוכה. vehatanya Rabbi Eliezer omer im hayta orcha yeter al
rochba pi shnayim afilu amah achat ein metalttelin betocha. The ברייתא braita
has רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer sounding just like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
It says רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if it's one אמה amah
more than twice as big, it's not acceptable. So how does... אמר
רבי ביבי בר אביי *Amar Rabbi Bibi bar Abaye* הכי תנן נמי
מתניתין *hachi tnan nami masnisin* יותר על פי שנים ברוחבה תנן *yoser
al pi shnayim berochbah tnan*. Basically read the ברייתא Braisah. *Baraita* into
the משנה Mishnah? *Mishnah*. When the, when our משנה *Mishnah* says that
if it's one אמה *amah* bigger than a perfect square, really it's
probably a mistake in text and really it should say if it's
one אמה *amah* bigger than being a two-to-one ratio. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי *ei hachi* if that's true, היינו רבי
יוסי *hainu Rabbi Yose*, isn't that רבי יוסי's *Rabbi Yose's* position that
it can be two-to-one and not more? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says איכא בינייהו ריבועא דריבועא דרבנן *ika beinaihu ribuah de-ribuah de-rabanan*. What
they're differing is about whether the square of the square of the
Rabbis. What does that mean? So רש"י *Rashi* says what it means
is where, what do you prefer? That the first position of רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* prefers it to be a square, but he'll allow
it to be a rectangle of two-to-one. Whereas the second position of
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* would actually prefer it to be a rectangle
because that was the size of the חצר chatzer המשכן *Chatzar HaMishkan*.
But he'll also obviously allow it to be a square, but he
actually would prefer it to be a rectangle. Now תוספות *Tosafot* says
what are you talking about prefer? Is this like a מצוה *mitzvah*
that there's like a לכתחילה *lechatchila*? You know, if it's allowed it's
allowed. And anyway, let's say somebody, there's a great line in תוספות
*Tosafot*, says let's say somebody actually has his courtyard this size. What?
You're going to tell him I want you to rearrange your courtyard?
I want you to reconfigure it from a rectangle to a square
or a square to a rectangle? It's a very nice תוספות *Tosafot*
because you know it sort of points out the reality of like
look, either tell me it's אסור assur. *assur* or it's מותר *muttar*.
Okay? But don't make me tell me to do it like למהדרין
*le-mehadrin* I should have a different courtyard than the one that I
have. So what does this idea of prefer mean? So תוספות *Tosafot*
actually says no, that the position is, it's a funny read, it's
an interesting read, he says that when you say twice as big
is no good, twice as long, more than twice as long, he
says one position would read the twice as long not twice as
long in terms of the actual length but even in terms of
the diagonal. So that that's what it means, that even if the
diagonal is twice as long as the width, which obviously then is
a more מחמיר *machmir* position. Okay, what I really don't understand talking
about what are you going to tell me to do reconfigure my
courtyard is the position that says it has to be exactly a
square, which seems to be at least רבי עקיבא's *Rabbi Akiva's* position
or רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* before it was changed as what are
they talking about? You know, is there a smaller size that's allowed
to be not a perfect square or anything that's לא הוקף לדירה
lo hukaf l'dira. *lo hukaf ledira* can only be a perfect square,
which is a very bizarre position. Anyway let's see where the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* goes. רבי יוסי אומר *Rabbi Yose omer* so now here's
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* allowing it to be twice as long. איתמר
itmar. *itamar* it was said אמר רבי יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל *Amar Rabbi Yosef amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel* הלכה halacha כרבי
יוסי *halacha k'Rabbi Yose* we rule like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* for
רב ביבי אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Rav Bibi amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel* הלכה כרבי עקיבא *halacha k'Rabbi Akiva* no, we rule like
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Now רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* was the one
that said remember, it's not only a question about square rectangle, the
question was about whether if it's לא הוקף לדירה lo hukaf l'dira
*lo hukaf ledira* did you need something else once it was limited
to בית סאתים beit satayim, *be-sa-atayim* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said
you didn't need anything else. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ותרוייהו
לקולא *v'tarvaihu le-kula* when we're ruling these two ways we're ruling the
lenient part of each person's position. Okay? Meaning the lenient part of
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that you don't need anything else if it's
limited to בית סאתים beit satayim, *be-sa-atayim* you're fine and the lenient
part of רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* that it can be a rectangle
up to two-to-one. וצריכא *v'tzricha* and you need both. אי אשמעינן הלכה
כרבי יוסי *Ei ashmeinan halacha k'Rabbi Yose* had you said you rule
like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* הוה אמינא *hava amina* עד דאיכא שומירה
או בית דירה beis dira, *ad d'ika shomira o beis dira* maybe
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* is addressing himself to square versus rectangle but
maybe he requires there to be some other type of thing to
make it more of a place of habitation like a guard house.
קא משמע לן הלכה כרבי עקיבא *ka mashma lan halacha k'Rabbi Akiva*
so you see we're ruling like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that as
long as you're limited to בית סאתים beit satayim. *be-sa-atayim* you don't
need anything else. ואי אשמעינן הלכה כרבי עקיבא *v'ei ashmeinan halacha k'Rabbi
Akiva* if you said like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* הוה אמינא *hava
amina* דאריך וקטין לא *d'arich v'katin lo* it can't be disproportionate, it
would have to be a perfect square, one can't be small and
the other long. קא משמע לן הלכה כרבי יוסי *ka mashma lan
halacha k'Rabbi Yose* so therefore we say the ruling is like רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. So we're very lenient about this בית סאתים beit
satayim. *be-sa-atayim* that it does not have to have anything else and
it can be up to a two-to-one. Now I should say it's
interesting to tie this into the point I made at the beginning
about to what degree does a רשות reshut. הרבים *reshus harabim* have
to be owned by the public. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* mentioned ownership
but again תוספות *Tosafot* says that was only private ownership would only
stop it being a רשות reshut. הרבים *reshus harabim* if also there
was מחיצות *mechitzas* and that made it like you couldn't say that
the רבים *rabim* were מבטל *mevatel* the מחיצה *mechitza*. But basically ownership
didn't matter. The רמב"ן *Ramban* said no, no, if it cannot be
a רשות הרבים *reshus harabim* under any circumstance unless it's publicly owned.
So this is an interesting parallel because here you have an idea
that a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshus hayachid* is not just about
your ownership by רבים *rabim* or יחיד *yachid*. I mean you have
something that's רבים *rabim* in a רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid *reshus hayachid*
like the חצר *chatzer*. Right? A חצר *chatzer* is a classic example
and that's part of the reason of עירוב eiruv *eruv*. But anyway
the חצר *chatzer* is a classic example of owned by multiple people
and still a רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid*, the חצר *chatzer* in front
of the houses. But even though it doesn't have to be owned
by a single individual it does have to be more connected to
the model of like a house, a בית דירה *beis dira*, a
place of habitation. So here becomes the issue about something that fundamentally
isn't a בית דירה *beis dira*. Not too big, not too long;
if it's too long maybe it's too much of a street and
not a place of like, you know, like a garden, but it
is interesting this concept of רשות היחיד where it's not ownership per
se but to some degree I think modeled after this idea of
a house. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara, moves on with this idea
of בית סאתיים beis sasayim and quotes a ברייתא. Braisah Somehow the
word איתמר. Okay. כרפף שיתר מבית סאתיים. Karpef she'yaser mibeis sasayim. So
here you have this כרפף, karpef, this like you know, כרפף karpef
is like a yard, but it's not like, you know, sort of
thinking about it like, I don't know, like like you know one
of those lots, like a vacant lot, that's bigger than בית סאתיים.
beis sasayim. So that's gonna be a problem cause a כרפף karpef
is not הוקף לדירה, hukaf l'dira, bigger than בית סאתיים beis sasayim
is no good. שהוקף לדירה She'hukaf l'dira but actually what you did
was when you put a fence around it, you actually were going
to use it for domicile purposes. I don't know what you were
using it for, a campground or something. Okay. And then נזרע רובו,
nizra rubo, but you planted like a vegetable garden in the majority
of it. Now a vegetable garden is a גינה. gina. Now we
know that a גינה gina is considered לא הוקף לדירה. hukaf l'dira
So now what you have is you have a a space that
is half one and half the other. How's its identity gonna be
defined? What's interesting first of all is that it's not like its
identity gets fixed based on the way that it was originally made.
Just cause you made a fence around it initially to make it
as a campground, it could be considered no longer הוקף לדירה hukaf
l'dira once it starts being used as a garden. Fine, that's if
it was completely converted. What if it wasn't completely converted? What if
half the majority of it was planted as a garden? So the
ברייתא Braisah, says הרי הוא כגינה, harei hu k'gina,
so the majority defines its identity and now it's like a garden
and so it's יותר מבית סאתיים yaser mibeis sasayim which is considered
no longer הוקף לדירה hukaf le-dira and therefore ואסור v'asur you can't
carry in it. נטע רובו Nata rubo however, let's say the majority
wasn't planted as a vegetable garden but trees. Oh, so trees then
trees don't stop it from being a place of habitation; like if
you have a vegetable garden you go into the garden to plant,
but otherwise it's off-limits. If you have trees, trees is a beautiful
thing to put into a park and for people to go and
spend time and to sit. So therefore if it's trees הרי הוא
כחצר ומותר, harei hu k'chatzer u'mutar, that doesn't undermine its status as
a חצר and therefore it is permissible. So the tree so שני
חידושים. shnei chidushim. Number one is that trees doesn't make it any
less of a בית דירה, but the bigger חידוש chidush is that
if it's once it can change its identity and it goes by
the majority. Okay. נזרע רובו. Nizra rubo. Now we're gonna analyze the
first part. The majority is planted that changes its identity as a
vegetable garden. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Amar Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua לא אמרן אלא יותר מבית סאתיים lo amran ela yaser
mibeis sasayim אבל בית סאתיים מותר. aval beis sasayim mutar. Although it
doesn't sound this way from the ברייתא, Braita he says if it
is
only a problem if the planted area is more than בית סאתיים.
beis sasayim. So then the actual garden itself is forbidden, it's more
than בית סאתיים beis sasayim לא הוקף לדירה hukaf le-dira, and it
makes the rest of the space forbidden. But if the garden was
less than בית סאתיים beis sasayim even if it was a majority,
it would not define the whole space. It doesn't go by majority
and it's only a problem when the garden itself is forbidden. And
then the הלכה is is that if you have one space that's
forbidden that's open into a space that otherwise would be permissible but
there's no wall between them, the other space is also forbidden. So
the גמרא Gemara says כמאן? k'man? Who is this going like? רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. That's like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתנן d'tnan רבי
שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer אחד גגות ואחד חצרות ואחד קרפיפות רשות
אחת הן לכלים ששבתו בתוכן ולא לכלים ששבתו בתוך הבית. echad gagot
v'echad chatzerot v'echad karpifot reshus achas hen l'keilim she'shavtu b'sochan v'lo l'keilim
she'shavtu b'soch habayis.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so this basically means
that without this fact that one of them was more than בית
סאתיים, beis sasayim, it would not have been a problem
even though you would have had a כרפף karpef opening up into
a גינה. gina. Those are considered conceptually different spaces. A garden, a
vegetable garden, whatever, and a כרפף karpef a lot. So there's a
whole discussion we'll see later that even if you have those that
are small and they're totally less than בית סאתיים beis sasayim and
totally a רשות היחיד but the same way we required an עירוב
eiruv from the houses and a courtyard, we might require an עירוב
eiruv to go from a lot to a garden and from a
garden to a roof and from one roof to the next, you
know, to the next roof and from a roof to a courtyard.
These might be considered to be distinct places and require an עירוב
to go from one to the other even though each one is
permissible. Now the גמרא Gemara is basically assuming that it gets a
status as a גינה gina full status and independent identity once it
hits בית סאתיים. beis sasayim. So it's saying how are you explaining
this משנה? You say when this garden becomes more than בית סאתיים
beis sasayim it becomes a place that's forbidden. And then it makes
the other part forbidden, which means that when it's less than בית
סאתים, beit satayim, everything is okay, even though you still have a
קרפף, karpaf, a lot, open into a גינה. gina. Why can you
carry from the lot to the גינה? gina? Those are different רשויות.
reshuyot. It must be that you even though they're both independently permissible,
that you're going like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that they're
all רשות אחת הן, reshut achat hen, they're all one one one
domain. לכלים ששבתו בתוכה le-kelim she-shavtu betokhah at least for the vessels
that that began there on שבת Shabbat ולא לכלים ששבתו בתוך הבית
ve-lo le-kelim she-shavtu betokh ha-bayit but not that you can take from
the house to those places because that is as from the house
to a courtyard is okay, from the house to one of those
places, that's already an unrelated רשות. Anyway, that's how the גמרא Gemara.
is saying, okay, if that's true, רבי שמעון נמי כיון דנזרע רובו
הוי
ההוא מיעוטא בטיל ליה לגבי רובא. Rabbi Shimon nami keivan de-nizra rubo
havei hahu miuta batil leh legabe ruba. So it's a very interesting
גמרא, Gemara the גמרא Gemara sort of doesn't it doesn't really connect
directly with רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's position and the גמרא Gemara doesn't
really bring any evidence, but the גמרא Gemara just says, I don't
like that read of this ברייתא because you're trying to make the
whole problem that the that the garden is too large and therefore
it becomes itself אסור. assur, I don't think you need to say
that, says the גמרא. Gemara Once the garden is the majority, even
if it's less than בית סאתים, beit satayim, it should define the
whole space, and the whole space should be considered a garden. So
why are you reading it that way? Quite funny because it was
no, okay, it was a little bit of a stretch, but but
there was nothing logical that made that position impossible. Anyway, let's see
what the גמרא says. אלא
אי איתמר הכי איתמר, Ela i itmar hachi itmar, fine, here's if
it was said, here's
how it was
said. האי מיעוטא שרי, Hai miuta shari, if it's a minority it's
permissible. So before we said if it's a majority, it's forbidden and
we said no, no, no, only if it's itself bigger than בית
סאתים. beit satayim And the גמרא said no, no, no, majority should
be enough. Okay, so now it's going the other way. If it's
a minority, it's permissible. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לא אמרן
אלא דלא הוי בית סאתים. Amar Rav Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua lo
amran ela de-lo havei beit satayim. That's only if it's not exactly
בית סאתים. beit satayim, Okay, אבל בית סאתים, aval beit satayim, once
it's בית סאתים, beit satayim אסור, assur, it's forbidden. So here's what
he's saying. Yes, if it's minority, it's permissible because the whole space
is defined by the lot and therefore and it was I don't
know you made it a campgrounds and it's הוקף לדירה hukaf le-dira
and you're fine as long as the minority is a garden. But
even that minority, once it gets to בית סאתים, beit satayim, even
if it's not יתר מבית סאתים. yeter mi-beit satayim. יתר מבית סאתים
yeter mi-beit satayim then again you have a space in this in
this fence that is not הוקף לדירה, hukaf le-dira but even if
it's exactly בית סאתים beit satayim. and not more than בית סאתים,
beit satayim it starts to be a problem. Why? Because then it
gets its independent identity as a גינה gina like we said before,
and now you have a גינה gina though a permissible גינה, gina,
but a גינה gina open up into a קרפף. karpaf. And that
is itself a problem even though each one independently is permissible. Why?
So the גמרא says כמאן? Ke-man? So the גמרא is saying like
this, כרבנן. Ke-rabbanan. It's going like the רבנן, Rabbanan, the רבנן Rabbanan
who argue on רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and say that a garden
and a קרפף karpaf are not the same רשות. And therefore even
when each one by itself is permissible because it's you know בית
סאתים beit satayim or less and so on, if there's no wall
between them, since you can't carry from one to the other, each
one by itself is also forbidden. So this is again a very
important principle that if something is open למקום האסור לו le-makom ha-assur
lo to a place that is forbidden to it, either that that
other place is יתר מבית סאתים yeter mi-beit satayim that's not הוקף
לדירה or that other place is just a different domain that you're
not allowed to carry into because of קרפף karpaf and גינה gina
according to the position of the חכמים, Chachamim, they say although those
are all רשות היחידs if they're different you can't carry from one
to the other. If therefore there's a difference, then it is going
to be then you are then if it's going to be open
one to the other, you can't carry in either of them. So
that's what we're saying. Yes, it goes by if once the garden
is majority, the whole space is defined. Once it's minority, fine, so
the whole space is okay from that perspective. But once the garden
itself is a בית סאתים, beit satayim, it becomes an independent space
open into the קרפף karpaf and not good because you can't carry
from one to the other. So the גמרא says רב ירמיה מדיפתי
מתני לכולה, Rav Yirmiyah mi-Difti matni le-kulah, רב ירמיה מדיפתי Rav Yirmiyah
mi-Difti says it leniently leniently, האי מיעוטא שרי Hai miuta shari if
it's a minority permissible, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לא אמרן
אלא בית סאתים. Amar Rav Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua lo amran ela
beit satayim. That's only up to a בית סאתים. beit satayim Up
to בית סאתים is
okay. That's a גינה gina open to a קרפף, karpaf, but you
know what? We rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we quoted before,
a גינה gina open to and a קרפף karpaf are one domain,
open to one another is okay. So up to a בית סאתים
is fine because it itself is permissible, so the גינה gina part
is permissible, the קרפף karpaf is permissible, it's okay they're open one
into the other. אבל יתר מבית סאתים Aval yeter mi-beit satayim as
soon as the garden hits more than a בית סאתים, even if
it's by minority, אסור, then it's forbidden because then it's a מקום
makom that's not הוקף לדירה bigger than a בית סאתים that is
therefore itself forbidden and open into the rest of the space, the
campground makes the campground forbidden as well. כמאן כרבי שמעון *Keman k'Rabbi
Shimon*, who is that going like? It's going like Rabbi Shimon that
says that if it were permissible it was בית סאתיים *beis sa'asayim*
or less even though each one would be one would be a
courtyard and one would be a excuse me one would be a
campground and one would be a garden, a כרפף *karpaf* and a
גינה *gina*, those are not considered distinct רשויות *reshuyot*. Now this is
extremely important. Number one, okay we have the debate between Rabbi Shimon
and the חכמים *Chachamim* that you could have places that are themselves
רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid* but of a different enough character that you
can't carry from one to the other without an עירוב *eruv*. And
the גמרא *Gemara* inclining towards the position of Rabbi Shimon that is
more lenient and says that no, if they're all רשות היחיד *reshus
hayachids* you don't really need an עירוב *eruv* from one to the
other, maybe from a house to one of them yes, but from
one of these to the other no, and that itself is not
a problem. But we also have the very important position that when
you do have one space that you can't carry to the other
space if there's no divider between them it's פתוח למקום האסור לו
*patuach l'makom ha'asur lo* then everything becomes forbidden. So that would be
לחכמים *l'Chachamim* if you have a גינה *gina* opening into a חצר
*chatzer* and it would become even according to Rabbi Shimon if within
a big space that's הוקף לדירה *hukaf l'dira* you had a place
that was bigger than בית סאתיים שלא הוקף לדירה *beis sa'asayim shelo
hukaf l'dira*. So the same way that place would be forbidden every
other place would be forbidden as well and this becomes a huge
issue in practical עירוב *eruv* because you can have an עירוב *eruv*
around a whole city but let's say you have within that space
a space that's not הוקף לדירה *hukaf l'dira*. What would that be?
Well I don't know let's say you had a park. So you'd
say oh a park? That's הוקף לדירה *hukaf l'dira*? And the גמרא
*Gemara* just talked about trees, you walk around, you rest, you do
things in. Okay. But what about if you had there a lake?
Let's say you have the lake in Central Park.
So people don't live in that lake. What do you do with
that? So there's a lot of leniencies in terms of how do
you define הוקף לדירה *hukaf l'dira*. Like some people say well because
you sort of float boats off of the edge of the lake,
actually in some places in Central Park you actually take boats throughout
the lake or you float these little toy boats and you could
have them go, they're mechanically controlled, but whatever, if you use a
part of that lake then the lake is also used by people
and it's also הוקף לדירה *hukaf l'dira*. But anyway one of the
big challenges that come with making an עירוב *eruv* is making sure
there's no space within the עירוב *eruv* that's bigger than בית סאתיים
*beis sa'asayim* that's not הוקף לדירה *hukaf l'dira*. So this הלכה *halacha*
that we're learning that seemed to be not relevant actually becomes one
of the major concerns in practical עירובין *ervin*. So we'll continue with
this tomorrow.